Records of the Senior Vice President of Operations
World Bank Group Archives
Records of the Senior Vice President of Operations
1967 - 1991
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_106
107.00 linear feet of textual records (approximate)
World Bank Group Archives
Senior Vice President of Operations
The Senior Vice President of Operations (SVPOP) has its origins in the Office of the Vice President of Burke Knapp (OVPBK), or also referred to as the Vice President of Operations. Burke Knapp's Vice Presidency was established on July 24, 1956, as one of three vice presidencies replacing the Office of the Vice President of Robert Garner (OVPRG). Knapp reported directly to the President. Knapp was assigned responsibility for the Bank's operational activities, including:
* lending operations
* economic, financial and technical research and analysis
* economic survey missions and other technical assistance activities; and
* liaison with other lending and aid agencies on above matters.
Knapp was also designated Chairman of the Staff Loan Committee and the Area Department Head meetings. The following departments reported to Knapp: the Departments of Operations, or Area Departments - Europe, Africa and Australasia, Asia and the Middle East, and Western Hemisphere; the Department of Technical Operations (TOD); and the Economic Staff (ECS).
In 1965, the TOD was terminated and replaced by the new Projects Department (PRJ). PRJ continued to report to OVPBK.
In 1966, with the Departure of Vice President Geoffrey Wilson (OVPGW), responsibility for the Information Department (INFO) was transferred to OVPBK. In 1967, the Information Department (INFO) was transferred to the Director of Development Services (DSD), who reported directly to the Office of the President (EXC).
In 1968, the Projects Department (PRJ) was separated from OVPBK, and reported to Director and Vice President of Finance (VPF) Siem Aldewereld.
In 1972, the OVPBK was terminated. Its functions were transferred to the newly established Office of the Senior Vice President of Operations (SVPOP), which was also headed by J. Burke Knapp.
The Senior Vice President of Operations (SVPOP) was established on October 1, 1972, and reported directly to the Office of the President (EXC). The SVPOP was created as part of the comprehensive 1972 Bank-wide Reorganization, which upgraded the Bank's former Area Departments to new Regional Vice Presidencies (RVPs), and transferred most of the technical staff involved in project preparation and implementation from the Projects Department (PRJ) to the newly created regional projects departments located in the new RVPs, in order to more effectively fuse sector skills with country knowledge. The SVPOP would assist the Bank President in managing the integrated projects and operations staffs. Freed from day-to-day operational tasks, Knapp would concentrate on establishing operating objectives, priorities and policies, planning, spurring innovation and improving overall quality, efficiency and effectiveness.
At the date of its establishment, the following vice presidencies composing the Bank's Operations Complex reported to SVPOP: the Regional Vice Presidencies (RVPs) of the Asia Vice Presidency (ASN), the East Africa Vice Presidency (EAN), the West Africa Vice Presidency (WAN), the Europe, Middle East, and North Africa Vice Presidency (EMN), and the Latin America and the Caribbean Vice Presidency (LCN); and the newly established Vice President of Central Projects (CPSVP). The SVPOP also served as the Chairman for the Bank's Loan Committee and the Operational Vice Presidents (OVP, formerly the Area Department Heads) meetings. The SVPOP was also supported by a Front Office team consisting of a Senior Operations Adviser, and a Personal Assistant to the SVPOP.
In 1974, the Asia Vice Presidency (ASN) was split into the South Asia Vice Presidency (ASN) and the East Asia and Pacific Vice Presidency (AEN).
In 1978, Ernest Stern succeeded Burke Knapp and the SVPOP was re-titled the Vice President of Operations (VPO). The functions and responsibilities remained unchanged. In 1980, the position of the VPO of the Operations Complex was again upgraded to Senior Vice President of Operations (SVPOP).
In 1982, the CPSVP was terminated and replaced by the Operations Policy Vice Presidency (OPSVP). Some staff of CPSVP were also absorbed by the new Energy and Industry Vice Presidency (EIS). Both reported to the SVPOP.
In January 1983, the Secretariat of the Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) was subordinated under the SVPOP; accompanying the move of Warren Baum, who served as Chairman of CGIAR, from the OPSVP to the Front Office of the SVPOP.
In May 1983, a new Vice President of Cofinancing (COF) was established with responsibility for all aspects of cofinancing policies and operations, and reported to theSVPOP. Later in 1983, the Office of the Management Systems and Budget (SVPMS) was added to the SVPOP Front Office to support budget formulation functions of the SVPOP and the Operations Complex.
In 1984, a Special Office for African Affairs was established in the Front Office of the SVPOP to coordinate and monitor a joint action program to expand technical and financial assistance to the countries of Sub-Saharan Africa.
In July 1984, the Operations Information Systems (SVPMI) Unit was established in theSVPOP Front Office to support and develop Management Information Systems (MIS) and database administration for the SVPOP and the Operations Complex.
In the May 1987 Reorganization, the Operations Complex was fundamentally restructured, the functions of the SVPOP redefined, and the SVPOP position given a new acronym (OPNSV). The main features of the reorganization were the consolidation of the former six Regional Vice Presidencies (RVP) into four, including: the Africa Vice Presidency (AFR); the Asia Vice Presidency (ASI); the Europe, Middle East, and North Africa Vice Presidency (EMENA); and the Latin America and Caribbean Vice Presidency (LAC). The reorganization also resulted in the creation of Country Departments (CDs), which combined functions previously divided between Programs and Projects Departments, and the establishment of Regional Technical Departments (TDs) taking on some of the functions of the former OPSVP and the EIS.
The newly reorganized Senior Vice President of Operations (OPNSV) served as a member of the President's senior management team and as Chief Operations Officer. The main responsibilities of the reorganized OPNSV included:
* advising the President on major operational issues
* acting as the Bank's spokesman on operational matters vis-a-vis Part I and Part II counties
* overseeing the formulation and implementation of the Bank's economic and social development programs; and
* ensuring the quality of the Bank's operational products and loans.
With the completion of the reorganization's second phase in September 1987, the following vice -presidencies and departments, which made up the Operations Complex, reported to OPNSV: the four Regional Vice Presidents (RVPs) of the Africa Vice Presidency (AFR), the Asia Vice Presidency (ASI), the Europe, Middle East, and North Africa Vice Presidency (EMENA), and the Latin America and Caribbean Vice Presidency (LAC); the newly established Vice President of Financial Intermediation (FIS); the Vice President of Cofinancing (COF); the Central Operations Department (COD); and the Economic Advisory Staff (EAS). The OPNSV also served as Chairman for the Operations Committee (OC, formerly the Loan Committee) and the Operations Policy Committee (OPC), which were composed of members from the Bank's Operations Complex.
The OPNSV was supported by a newly reorganized Front Office, or Operations Staff (OPN), which included: the Director of Operations Staff (OPN); the Special Adviser, Lending and Budget Operations; the Special Adviser, Personnel, Budget, and Information Management; the Chief Personnel Officer; and the Special Assistant to the OPNSV. The Operations Information Systems (SVPMI) Unit acronym was changed to the OPNMI, and the Office of the Management Systems and Budget (SVPMS) acronym was changed to the OPNMS.
Moeen Qureshi succeeded Ernest Stern as the new Senior Vice President for Operations (OPNSV).
In January 1989, the OPNMI was upgraded to a division and renamed the Operations Information Services Division (OPNIS).
In June 1989,the FIS was combined with the COF and renamed the Cofinancing and Financial Intermediation Vice Presidency (CFS). This was expected to enhance the Bank's ability to deal with debt issues and improve the service to the Regions and the borrowers.
In 1991, following the appointment of World Bank President Lewis T. Preston, the senior management structure was heavily reorganized, and the Bank's senior vice presidencies were abolished, including OPNSV. As a result, the Economic Advisory Staff (EAS) was terminated, and its staff and functions were absorbed by the new Development Policy Group (DPG) located in the Development Economics Vice Presidency (DEC); the Central Operations Department (COD) was transferred to the Vice President of Sector Policy and Research (OSPVP); and the Vice President of Cofinancing and Financial Advisory Services (CFS) reported to the newly appointed Managing Director Attila Karaosmanoglu. The four RVPs reported to Office of the President (EXC) and the newly established Managing Directors, who served as a broad administrative oversight team that supported the President. The Office of the Management Systems and Budget (OPNMS) of the OPNSV Front Office was terminated, and the Operations Information Services Division (OPNIS) functions were split between the new Information Services Division (CODIS) in the Central Operations Department (COD) and the Budget Policy and Systems Division (PBDPS) in the Planning and Budgeting Department (PBD).
Published
Records of Vice President of Operations and SVPOP J. Burke Knapp
The fonds includes records maintained by Vice President and Senior Vice President of Operations (SVPOP) J. Burke Knapp. The records include memoranda sent between Knapp and Bank President Robert McNamara from 1967 to 1978. Much of the memoranda are originals authored by Knapp and annotated and sent back by the President. There are also copies of records addressed to McNamara by other staff and copies of minutes of the President's Council or other meetings with the President. The memoranda to the President focus on IBRD and IDA lending programs, papers on financial and lending policy, loan overruns, and other particular loan issues.
Knapp records also include a set of briefs for the 1972 Annual Meeting. The briefs contain briefing memoranda and reports on the politico-economic situation and the Bank's lending program in individual member countries. In preparation for scheduled meetings between the Bank President and the delegations of membercountries, the briefs provide a summarized background for the meeting, talking points for the President, summaries of subjects likely to be raised by the delegation, and a list of delegates. Filed with some of the briefs are related Country Program Papers (CPP). In addition to briefs for individual countries, filed at the beginning of the series are briefs on the African and Latin American Caucuses, the Asian Development Bank (ADB), and the European Investment Bank (EIB).
Records of OPNSV Moeen Qureshi
The fonds also includes records maintained by Senior Vice President of Operations (OPNSV) Moeen Qureshi. The records consist of briefing materials prepared for Qureshi from 1987 to 1991. Briefings cover his foreign travel and any formal meetings he attended in New York or Washington, DC. In addition, there are records for his August 17 - September 8, 1984, trip to London, Pakistan, New Zealand, Australia, and Japan. A typical briefing file contains: Qureshi's itinerary and schedule; biographies of people with whom he would be meeting; outlines, drafts, and copies of speeches he delivered; press releases; correspondence; conference agenda and programs; and background papers regarding the Bank's relationship with the countries visited.
Joint IMF-World Bank Annual Meeting briefs prepared for Qureshi are also included for the years 1988 to 1990. The briefs consist of a separate folder for each day of the Annual Meeting. A typical folder contains Qureshi's schedule for that day and a sub-folder for each event he was scheduled to attend. The briefs also include: lists of delegates attending each event; agenda for meetings; Annual Meeting briefs for each country whose delegation met with Qureshi; talking points for and copies of speeches for Qureshi or President Barber Conable; copies of Conable's schedule for the day; and seating charts.
Qureshi's records also include materials concerning the 1987 Bank-wide reorganization from 1986 to 1989. The records consist of: memoranda exchanged between Conable, Qureshi and members of the Operations Complex regarding implementation of the reorganization plan and specific staff appointments; copies of memoranda from Conable updating Bank staff on the reorganization; records outlining interim personnel procedures; Steering Committee issuances regarding staff selection, redeployment, and redundancy; copies of letters from Conable to specific staff affected by the reorganization; Bank press releases; the Support Unit Task Force Report; and studies completed by an external management consulting firm. Much of the records concern implementation of the reorganization within the Operations Complex. Specific records focus on the Operations Task Force Report, which includes: comments from staff regarding that report; draft position descriptions; and memoranda regarding the staff selection and allocation process.
The Qureshi records also contain records related to country lending operations from 1987 to 1991. The records consist of memoranda, letters, cables, reports, studies, and minutes of meetings regarding the Bank's lending policies in specific countries or, in the case of donor countries, aid coordination. The records also include briefing papers prepared for Qureshi and/or President Conable prior to meetings with country representatives, agenda and minutes of meetings of Qureshi or Conable with country representatives, minutes of meetings of Bank Executive Directors, and Bank mission reports. Much of the records include Qureshi's annotations. Issues discussed in the correspondence include technical assistance, economic reforms, environmental impact of Bank policies, political events in a country and their implication for Bank loans and operations, and special grants in response to natural disasters.
Lastly, incoming and outgoing correspondence and memoranda between Qureshi, the OPNSV Front Office Staff, and members of the Operations Complex are included for the years 1987 to 1989.
Records of Special Assistant Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala
The fonds also includes records maintained by Ngozi Okonjo-Iweala when she served as Special Assistant to the Senior Vice President of Operations (OPNSV) Moeen Qureshi. This includes records maintained by Okonjo-Iweala related to major borrowing countries from 1987 to 1991. These records consist mostly of copies of correspondence and reports on lending operations and recent developments in borrowing countries. Background materials and reports of meetings held between Bank officials and official representatives of the borrowing countries are also included. County Strategy Papers (CSP) are found in some records. Among the most discussed lending issues are structural adjustment, privatization, technical assistance, and late payments. Some of the records contain Okonjo-Iweala's correspondence with the staff from the Regional Vice Presidencies (RVPs) officials, her handwritten and typed notes to Qureshi on lending issues, and her handwritten notes taken at meetings she attended.
Okonjo-Iweala records also consist of business plans for the OperationsComplex from 1989 to 1991. The records consist of internal memoranda and reports detailing planned lending expenditures for FY 1991 to 1993 and FY 1992 to 1994. The business plans are broken down by Region, therein by country and sector with reference to the Bank's country lending strategies. Breakdowns on IBRD versus IDA lending are also given. The business plans are heavily annotated by Okonjo-Iweala.
Okonjo-Iweala records also include memoranda, reports, and correspondence on a variety of operational and administrative matters relating to the functions of the OPNSV from 1989 to 1991. Records related to operational matters include records related to the following topics: cofinancing; private sector development; the IDA Ninth Replenishment; the Gulf crisis; and the Bank's interaction with international organizations. Records related to administrative matters include: preparation for the 1990 Annual Meeting; records related to a Senior Operations mangers' retreat; and records related to pay, annual leave,the staff retirement plan, and actions regarding specific staff members. Filed under "Front Office" are also records regarding administrative matters of security, document formats, and the United Way Campaign. There are also records containing briefing notes for trips undertaken or meetings attended by Qureshi.
Okonjo-Iweala records also includes materials maintained for the Operations Committee (OC) from 1989 to 1991. Arranged by country, most of the records include: Okonjo-Iweala's copies of formal minutes of the OC meetings; her handwritten notes taken when she attended the OC meetings; and postscripts on discussions of Country Strategy Papers (CSP) by the OC. Included with the minutes are copies of CSPs, Initiating Memoranda, and reports and recommendations accompanying requests for loans and credits submitted by the country to the OC. Some draft CSPs submitted to Okonjo-Iweala are annotated with her comments.
Lastly, Okonjo-Iweala records include internal memoranda, correspondence, and reports from 1990, which were primarily sent between her, the OPNSV Moeen Qureshi, the OPNSV Front Office Staff, and members of the Operations Complex.
Records of Senior Adviser, Lending and Budget Operations, Cosmas Linus Robless
The fonds also includes records of Cosmas Linus Robless, who served as Senior Advisor for Lending and Budget Operations to OPNSV Moeen Qureshi, from 1987 to 1991. Records include subject files consisting of: memoranda; correspondence; reports; position papers; and guidelines regarding Operations Complex programs and policies. Other records focus on the topics of: annual sector reviews; the Field Offices Task Force; overdue service payments; the Bank's response to the Gulf Crisis; graduation from the Bank; and program goals for the Operations Complex. Correspondence, memoranda, and reports sent and received by Robless are also included.
Robless records also consist of materials related to the Ad Hoc Committee on Board Procedures from 1990 to 1991, which sought to improve bank procedures performed by the Bank's Executive Directors (ED) for reviewing country assistance strategies and policy formulation in Bank operations. The records include: correspondence and memoranda; meeting minutes of the Ad Hoc Committee; draft Ad Hoc Committee reports prepared for the EDs; terms of reference prepared for EDs; and work programs prepared for the EDs for consideration.
Lastly, his records also include copies of Country Strategy Paper (CSP) postscripts prepared for the Operations Committee (OC) from 1991. The CSP postscripts summarize the review, and subsequent actions taken by the OC for a particular CSP.
Front office adviser records
The fonds also includes records maintained by various advisers who served in the Front Office for SVPOP Ernest Stern and his successor OPNSV Moeen Qureshi from 1979 to 1989. The front office records reflect the activities of the SVPOP/OPNSV. The records include: SVPOP yellow sheets, or handwritten project lending notes; decision memoranda and comments prepared by advisers on behalf of the SVPOP for the Loan Committee; Loan Committee log book prepared by advisers; board papers, briefs, and schedules prepared for meetings with the Executive Board of Directors; memoranda regarding Project Completion Reports (PCR) submitted to OPNSV from the Central Operations Department (COD); memoranda regarding Women in Development (WID) country assessments submitted to the OPNSV from the Economic Advisory Staff (EAS); working papers submitted to OPNSV from the Policy, Planning, and Research (PPR) Complex for review; standard budget tables submitted to SVPOP from the Division Chief of the Planning and Budget Department (PBD); and memoranda, budget reports, and other records related to liaison with United Nations cooperative programs.
Communications and Meetings with Area Department Heads (later Operational Vice Presidents)
The fonds includes memoranda address by Ernest Stern as (Vice President (1978-1980) and Senior Vice President (1980-1987) of Operations to the Operational/Regional Vice Presidents. Topics of memoranada include lending policies, programming, and lending activities.
The fonds also includes memoranda and minutes from the weekly meetings of the Area Department Heads and its replacement of the Operational Vice Presidents (OVP, renamed after 1972 Reorganization) from 1968 to 1986. The records dated from 1968 to 1978 were maintained by J. Burke Knapp when he served as Chairman for the Area Department Heads and the OVP as the Vice President of Operations and SVPOP. The recordsdated 1979 to 1986 are maintained by Vice President of Operations (VPO) and SVPOP Ernest Stern.
Country lending and strategy records
The fonds also includes records related to the Bank's country lending operations from 1981 to 1991. Records were maintained by Senior Adviser for Lending and Budget Operations Cosmas L. Robless, and OPNMS Senior Programming Officers Larry Smucker and Manuel Benedito. The records include: lending review records focused on lending projects in the Regions for the fiscal years 1982 to 1983 and 1988 to 1994; lending program status records and reports focused on reporting lending project status to the Bank's Board of Executive Directors; records related to lending allocations for IBRD/IDA loans; records related to the Five Year Lending Program, 1984-1989; records related to the IDA Ninth Replenishment for lending operations; and Country Briefs prepared for various countries in the Regions from 1985 and 1987, which outlined an economic profile of a country, lending programming, and reform actions taken.
Budget formulation and review records